Guide to the Ron Howard papers, 1958-1999 MS0766.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ron Howard papers
1958-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS0766.UA
10 Linear Feet
Collection include photographs (including many campus buildings no longer extant) and slides (including commencements, buildings, distinguished alumni, President Lloyd Elliott, Jack Friedenthal, Edward "Skip" Ghnem, the GW mascot, Elmer Kayser, the men's and Women's basketball teams, President Trachtenberg, the University Yard, Gates, campus and Washington scenes, and other personalities. Artifacts include banners, key chains, buttons, towels, medals, tickets to Ronald Reagan Honorary Degree ceremony, videotapes, including Alumni Weekend, 1985, Reagan convocation, commencements, Walter Cronkite, Recruiting tapes and an award given to Ronald Howard. The collection spans the years 1958-99.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to University Archives by Alumni House in 1999, following the death of Mr. Howard.
Biographical Note
Ronald Warren Howard (1934-August 19, 1999) came to GW in 1964 as a counselor in the Admissions Office, and would serve the university for over thirty years, until his death in 1999 following a six year battle with cancer. Howard graduated from Central College in Pella, Iowa (B.A. in English, 1956) and worked as an admissions counselor at Carthage College in Kenosha, Wisconsin before taking a similar position here. At GW he became assistant director of admissions and foreign students admissions officer before moving to the Development Office, where he served as director of alumni support from 1973-80. In September 1980 he began work in the Alumni Office as associate director of alumni relations. He served as Director of Alumni Relations from June 1986-1989, and then became the first full-time director of the Alumni Admissions Program, which mobilized volunteer alumni nationwide to help recruit prospective GW students from their particular regions.
Ron Howard traveled the country spreading the message of GW to prospective students, as well as alumni. He was such an enthusiastic ambassador of the university that he became known as "Mr. GW" and "Mr. Alumni." Howard won the GW Award in 1977, given in "special recognition to those people who have made The George Washington University a better place to be." Ron Howard was an enthusiastic photographer. He free lanced for the student newspaper the Hatchet, and some of his images appeared in various campus publications as well. His enthusiasm to capture through the lens of a camera the people and events surrounding the university has been a benefit to the preservation of GW's history.
(Biographical information compiled from "GW Magazine" article, Fall 1993 and "By George" article September 7, 1999)
Collection Scope and Content
The collections consists of five series: photographs, slides, memorabilia, videotapes, and personal awards, etc. from Ron Howard.
Materials in this collection include photographs (including many campus buildings no longer extant) and slides (including commencements, buildings, distinguished alumni, President Lloyd Elliott, Jack Friedenthal, Edward "Skip" Ghnem, the GW mascot, Elmer Kayser, the men's and Women's basketball teams, President Trachtenberg, the University Yard, Gates, campus and Washington scenes, and other personalities. Artifacts include banners, key chains, buttons, towels, medals, tickets to Ronald Reagan Honorary Degree ceremony, videotapes, including Alumni Weekend, 1985, Reagan convocation, commencements, Walter Cronkite, Recruiting tapes and an award given to Ronald Howard. The collection spans the years 1958-99.
The collection came to the archives with very liitle order to it, and almost no items identified by Mr. Howard. Every effort was made to correctly identify people and events, and assign a date range, although at times this was difficult to do. Photos and slides of particular events were sorted and kept in the same folder/tray, but some images may actually belong to other events. Years have been assigned using clues from the images themselves (for example the date on the back of the photo or slide, or the cover of a Commencement program someone might be holding in a photo), but most of the dates are approximations.
Collection Organization
Organized in five series: Photographs, Slides, Memorabilia, Videotapes, and Certificates and awards.
Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Campuses; Hatchet; Color slides; Photography; Photographs; Howard, Ronald W.; Friedenthal, Jack H.; George Washington University; Trachtenberg, Stephen Joel; Gnehm, Edward W. (Edward William); George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Reagan, Ronald; George Washington University--History; Cronkite, Walter; Elliott, Lloyd H.
- Photographs, 1975-1998; MS0766 Series 1; 6 Linear feet (Box 11, Box 12, Box 9, Box 10, Box 7, Box 8, Box 5, Box 6, Box 3, Box 4, Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of 5,000 images. They range in date from c.1975-c.1998, with the bulk from 1985-1998. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject headings such as Basketball, Commencements, Distinguished Alumni Award Winners (which may also have photos of the winter commencement for that year, and include Honorary Degree recipients), GW Presidents Lloyd Elliott and Stephen Joel Trachtenberg, and various specific events (including alumni gatherings, Walter Mondale's campaign visit to GW in 1984, Bob Hope's visit in 1985, and the 1990 summit with President Bush and Mikhail.) Mr. Howard also took photos of celebrities such as Jerry Lewis, Cokie Roberts, Walter Cronkite and Robert Redford, and politicians such as Marion Barry, Dick Gephardt, Dan Quayle, and Walter Mondale.
  Mr. Howard's personal photos were varied and many, and a sampling has been maintained as a sub-series. These are generally photos not linked to the university or unidentifiable, and includes individuals, vacation trips, and Howard's life before coming to GW.
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Academic procession with fife and drum corps going to Marvin Center, 1985 ca. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: ABC news show, Viewpoint at GWU, 1985 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Admissions Open House, 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni event - miscellaneous, 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni function with President Trachtenberg and Edward "Skip" Gnehm, (with negatives), 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni function (?) (with negatives), 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni group, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni house staff, 1983-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni house staff, 1983-1998 ca. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni house staff, 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni house staff - retirement of unidentified woman, 1996 ca. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni reunion w/J. William Fulbright (with negatives), 1984 ca. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Alumni staff picnic with President Elliott, 1985 ca. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: America's Gate, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Armey, Dick & Dick Gephardt Alumni Office special event (with negs), 04/1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Auerbach, Red, 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Auerbach, Red w/Bob Farris & Elmer Kayser, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Basketball banquet, 1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Basketball cheerleaders and ceremony with Bob Farris and Pat Tallent, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Basketball-Miscellaneous, 1982-1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Basketball, Misc. men and women's, 1977-1995 ca. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Basketball team reunion with Dallas Shirley, et al, 1992 ca. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Buchanan, Pat at Meet the Press (with negatives), 1990 ca. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Buchanan, Pat at Crossfire show at GWU, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Buckley, William F. & Firing Line at GWU (with negatives), 1997 ca. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Burns, Jacob with Warren Burger, et al, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Campaign for Walter Mondale, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Campus events-miscellaneous, 1982 ca. 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Campus scenes - University Yard, etc., 1984 ca. 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Cheerleaders, 1995 ca. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Cheerleaders at GW basketball game, 1996 ca. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Class ring, 1990 ca. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Colonial women... boosters banquet, 1990 ca. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Colonials Inc. gathering, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Colonials Inc. function (with negatives), 1985 ca. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Colonial Inauguration, 1997 ca. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement-miscellaneous commencements and convocations, 1975 ca. 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement - Winter (with negatives), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement - President Elliott with Marcus Cunliffe and others, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement-Winter, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement, including admission ticket (with negatives), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement - Law School at Smith Center, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement-in Marvin Theatre, 1985 ca. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    General note
    See also videotapes
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement - Medical School at Lisner Auditorium, 1996 ca. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Chief Justice Rehnquist, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Bill Cosby, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Bob Dole (with negatives), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Bob Dole (with negatives), 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement (with negatives), 1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Daniel Inouye, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commencement w/Hillary Clinton, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Commission on Presidential Debates at Betts Theatre, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Community Program with Sandra Holley (DAA winner 1988), 1995 ca. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Construction of the academic center, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Crew team race, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Cronkite, Walter, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    See also videotapes - Kalb Report
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Cronkite, Walter with Abba Eban, 1996 ca. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Dallas, Shirley award (with negatives), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Debate at GW w/mayoral candidates Anthony Williams & Carol Schwartz, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Dedication for Jackie Kennedy Onassis Hall (with negatives), 1995 ca. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Democratic Party State convention with Mark Warner (GW class of 1977) (with negatives), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Denver, John and Jake Garn, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished Alumni/Honorary Degree recipients (?), 1950-1990 ca. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1980 ca. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners (with negatives), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners (with negatives), 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners (with negatives), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winners, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Distinguished alumni award winner, Chairman of the Joint Chief of Staff, Shalikashivili (with negatives), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Donaldson, Sam, 1995 ca. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Dorothy Betts Theatre - Pirates of Penzance (?), 1980 ca. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Dorothy Betts Theatre - Rehearsal for play, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd, President of GW, 1970 ca.1995 ca. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd, 1985 ca. 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd and Marion Barry, 1988 ca. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd and wife Betty receiving certificate of appreciation from the Alumni Association, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd and wife with Edward Gnehm, 1994 ca. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd and wife with Edward Gnehm, 1995 ca. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd, Dave Clarke, and Oliver Carr, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd with faculty in house (with negatives), 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd meeting with a group (with negatives), 1980 ca. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd receiving a medal, 1995 ca. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott, Lloyd's seventy-fifth Birthday Party in New York City, 1990 ca. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Elliott School function - The Planetary Society w/Carl Sagen, 1990 ca. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Event with Hillary Clinton, Barbara Bush, Rosslyn Carter, 1994 ca. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    See also Acc #1021
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Excellence in student life awards, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Family weekend (with negatives), 1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Family weekend, 1995 ca. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Freedman, Mike with Sally Holland and Bernard Kalb, 1996 ca. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Friedenthal, Jack H., (Dean of Law School, 1989-1998 ), 1997 ca. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Friedenthal, Jack with Alan Dershowitz (with negatives), 1995 ca. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Gelman Library - 10th anniversary celebration, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Gnehm, Edward "Skip" at the United Nations (with negatives), 1997 ca. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Gnehm, Edward "Skip" -White House swearing in ceremony as Director of Foreign Services, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    See also Acc#776 and Acc#417, Spring 1991
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Gnehm, Edward "Skip" and others, 1980-1995 ca. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Going away party for staff member in President Elliott's office (with negatives), 1985 ca. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Graham, Stedman & Jack Morton (with negatives), 1996 ca. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW band with Mark Warner (GW graduate and Governor of Virginia), 1995 ca. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW forum on the 1996 Presidential Election (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW function w/President & Mrs. Elliott (with negatives), 06/1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW mascot "George", 1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW staff at CBS TV Station WBZ-TV4, 1996 ca. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW theatre, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: GW welcomes Mike Jarvis as men's basketball coach (with negatives), 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Gymnastics team exhibition, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Holley, Sandra (Distinguished Alumni Award winner, 1988), 1997 ca. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Homecoming (Steve Frick & Doug Vanderwal), 1985 ca. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Homecoming (with negatives), 1986 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Hooding ceremony, 1998 ca. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Hooding ceremony in Betts Theatre (with negatives), May 13, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Hope, Bob and the Troubadours (with negatives), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Justice Harry Blackman at function (with negatives), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kalb report, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kalb report, 1997 ca. (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kalb report w/Jesse Jackson, 1996 ca. (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kalb report w/G. Gordan Liddy & Douglas Wilder, 1997 ca. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kalb report w/Richard Lugar, 1997 ca. (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kayser, Elmer, 05/1984 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kayser, Elmer & friends, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kayser, Elmer Louis with GW faculty and staff in publicity shot, 1975 ca. (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Kemp, Jack at Crossfire show in Marvin Center, 1997 ca. (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: King, Larry & Barry Manilow, 1995 ca. (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: King, Larry & Martina Navratilova receiving honorary degrees, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Law school alumni, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Law school Commencement (with negatives), 1997 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: March to conquer cancer (with negatives), 1998 ca. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Martin Luther King Convocation, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Meeting of women, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game at GW, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game v. St. Josephs (with negatives), 1985 ca. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game v. Rhode Island, 02/1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game, 02/1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game (with negatives), 11/1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - George Washington University, Events, and Campus: Men's basketball game, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)